<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Funerall elegies, vpon the most vntimely death of the honourable and most hopefull, Mr. Iohn Stanhope, sonne and heire to the Right Honourable Philip Lord Stanhope, Baron of Shelford vvho deceased in Christ-church at Oxford, the 18. of Iuly, 1623.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852995</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18353</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12936)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18353)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1035:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Funerall elegies, vpon the most vntimely death of the honourable and most hopefull, Mr. Iohn Stanhope, sonne and heire to the Right Honourable Philip Lord Stanhope, Baron of Shelford vvho deceased in Christ-church at Oxford, the 18. of Iuly, 1623.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 50, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by George Purslowe] for Ralph Mab,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXIV. [1624]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A collection of English and Latin verse by various Oxonians.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>The inserted preliminary leaf "Ad lectorem" is in two settings; line 5 of verse has (1) "Causa" or (2) "causa".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Leaf H1 torn; p. 36-50 from Folger Shakespeare Library copy spliced at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stanhope, John, d. 1623 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18353:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18353:1"/>
            <p>FVNERALL ELEGIES, VPON THE MOST VNTIMELY DEATH OF the Honourable and moſt hopefull, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> IOHN STANHOPE, Sonne and Heire to the Right Honourable PHILIP Lord STANHOPE, Baron of <hi>Shelford:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVHO DECEASED IN Chriſt-church at OXFORD, the 18. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1623.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>London printed for</hi> Ralph Mab. <hi>MDCXXIV.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18353:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18353:2"/>
            <head>Ad Lectorem.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>OFficioſus Amor lachrimas effudit ab vrna</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quam raptìm ingeſtas Muſa latere velit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melpomenen moerore ſuo ne crede ſuperbam;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faſtum ô quid neſcit, ſi modo luctus habet?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tu ſolum expendas, quanta eſt huic cauſa dolori,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cum ſapiat, quaſi nunc prompta, Querela vetus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18353:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18353:3"/>
            <head>IN AMICISSIMVM MEVM.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>GEmma domus noſtrae, Muſarum dulers ocelle</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flos Parnaſstaci, deliciae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> chori,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Defunctum ſequor obſequijs, complector &amp; vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heu quot corporibus dignior vmbra tua eſt?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non eſt fictus amor, non eſt vmbratilis ardor,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vmbra places, videar corporis vmbra tui.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henricus Percy,</signed> Comitis Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briae Filius.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18353:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd haſt thou left vs then (Deare Soule?) muſt wee</l>
               <l>Comfort our eyes, no more beholding thee?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uldſt thou bee ſo much a proficient here,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> dye ſo ſoone in thy firſt yeere?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ill thou be thus a Graduate, to ſhine</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> already, and there turne Diuine?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gree, whoſe luſter quite defaces</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e Hoods, and Academicke graces.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h miſtooke thee; meaſuring thee a man</l>
               <l>By thy Soules Elle, not by thy bodies Span.</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou beene duller, thou perchance mightſt haue</l>
               <l>Gone but a ſlow and foot-pace to thy graue:</l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch of Fate had not bin ſtir'd: the Skies</l>
               <l>Would not ſo greedy ſnatch ſo meane a prize:</l>
               <l>Thy quicknes kild thee, ripenes was thy death,</l>
               <l>Running to goodnes, thou ranſt out of breath.</l>
               <l>How didſt thou pitch beyond thy yeeres! how ſage,</l>
               <l>How wiſe, how ſtaid, how elder than thy age!</l>
               <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t manly grauity was knowne to houſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in thy ſmooth then others wrinckled browes?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> different from the common Nobler ſort,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> here for faſhion onely come and ſport,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> weare a gawdy Gowne! and then with eaſe</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Streets, and learne the Colledges,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ape ſome few ends of Ieſts, wherewith hereafter:</l>
               <l>To branch diſcourſe, and entertaine a laughter!</l>
               <l>That nere reach further than the myſticall</l>
               <l>Science of <hi>Tennis,</hi> and (their Spheare) the Ball;</l>
               <l>Or elſe to weild ſome Fencers woodden toole,</l>
               <l>Or ſweat a Night-cap in the Dancing-ſchoole.</l>
               <l>To cracke a Lute-ſtring, and ſuch worthy Arts,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18353:4"/>
               <l>In others, Complements, in great men, parts.</l>
               <l>Thy Studies were more ſerious as thy lookes,</l>
               <l>While others Bandyed thou waſt toſſing Bookes,</l>
               <l>Buſied in Paper, and collecting there,</l>
               <l>Gemmes to ſticke in thy mind, not in thine eare.</l>
               <l>Me thinks I ſee thee yet cloſe by thy ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Reaching ſome choyce Booke from thy furniſht ſhelfe,</l>
               <l>Looſe the ſilke ſtrings, and with a willing paine,</l>
               <l>To read, and thinke, and write, and read againe.</l>
               <l>Thus didſt thou ſpend thy lifes ſhort day, till night,</l>
               <l>Deaths night oretooke thee, and put out thy light.</l>
               <l>This ſable Curtaine was too ſoone oreſpred,</l>
               <l>Thy day-taske done, to bring thee to thy bed.</l>
               <l>Yet happy ſoule, whoſe firſt night did begin</l>
               <l>In Death, vndarkned with the night of ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18353:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>VT nova ſubſiliunt acciſo germinae trunco,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et reficit pennae damna cadentis olor;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic vbi Matris honor cecidit Stanhopia proles,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sarcina mox orbam non ſinit eſse nova.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Primitias vteri, quae coelo debita ſors eſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Soluiſti Mater, quid potes inde queri?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At Calum excambit foetum, ſimilem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> reponit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Num potes hoc damnum dicere? munus erat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui ſic interijt, non interijſse videtur</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Natalem fato, ſed reparaſse ſuo.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ier. Thorp. Art Mag. ex Aede Chriſti.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18353:5"/>
            <head>A Funerall Elegie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for a teadious famine, or a ſiege</l>
               <l>Threatning vs al, our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try &amp; our Liege:</l>
               <l>So do we grieue for thee, each neighbour</l>
               <l>Weeps to the indangering of an eye;</l>
               <l>As if the loſſe were his, or he had ſold by</l>
               <l>His Patrimony, and had ſpent the gold.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Currantoes, <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> and the fate</l>
               <l>And Maſſacres of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In this ſpring tide, and flood of griefe are loſt,</l>
               <l>As raine drops in a ſtreame, that in the vaſt</l>
               <l>Ocean, this hath ſo fill'd our hearts, eyes, eares,</l>
               <l>That we want ſence of other cares then theſe.</l>
               <l>If in a drowth this accident had beene,</l>
               <l>Thou hadſt not, Fate, committed ſuch a ſinne.</l>
               <l>he peoples tribute had repair'd the loſſe</l>
               <l>Of the mad dog-ſtarres fury, and this croſſe;</l>
               <l>For with their teares the parched earth had beene,</l>
               <l>As after plent'ous raine, fruitfull and greene.</l>
               <l>By ſhould heauens drops now longer mixe with ours,</l>
               <l>But theſe vnited conduits, doubled ſhowres,</l>
               <l>Trent would vnruly grow, and his proud waues</l>
               <l>Would make our habitations then our graues.</l>
               <l>As the ſunne ſnow: ſo griefe melts vs, and you,</l>
               <l>Whereſe're we goe, may tract vs by our dew.</l>
               <l>The State-men of this loſſe ſuch notice take,</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18353:6"/>
               <l>They'le not doe buſineſſe, 'till they'ue wept for's ſake.</l>
               <l>With theſe Inferiors ioyne, from th' Collyers eye</l>
               <l>You may take inke to write an Elegie,</l>
               <l>And in their fields of hay the Countrey-men</l>
               <l>Doe weepe, as if they'd haue it grow againe.</l>
               <l>Our ſinne hath bred this croſſe: ſo <hi>Adams</hi> vice</l>
               <l>Did diſinherite him of Paradiſe.</l>
               <l>His death of ours, nay vnborne Babes will miſſe,</l>
               <l>And feele his abſence. who had brought a bliſſe</l>
               <l>To them, to all of them. For as we ſee</l>
               <l>A goodly, ſpreading, large, and well-limbd tree</l>
               <l>Doth guard the vnderwood, and doth immure</l>
               <l>The houſes neere, which by it are ſecure;</l>
               <l>So from all tempeſt, from all rage of winde</l>
               <l>He would haue fenc'd his neighbours, and haue ſhin'd</l>
               <l>Like Lights in Watch-towres, which are ſet to ſaue</l>
               <l>Paſſengers from Rockes, and fury of the Waue.</l>
               <l>This may coniectur'd bee, from what we ſaw,</l>
               <l>His youth did beare, and promiſe. For if by</l>
               <l>The foote of <hi>Hercules</hi> with Geometrie</l>
               <l>His true proportion was collected, may</l>
               <l>Not we on the ſame grounds proceed, and ſay</l>
               <l>On ſight of the foundation, this had beene</l>
               <l>As faire an edifice as e're was ſeene,</l>
               <l>If't had gone on? it is prophane to ſay,</l>
               <l>The Builder wanted skill, and ſtuffe to lay</l>
               <l>A perfect roofe on what he had began,</l>
               <l>And could not end this Maſter-piece of Man,</l>
               <l>And therefore daſht it out, Wee all doe know</l>
               <l>We were vnworthy of ſo great a flow,</l>
               <l>And ſtreame of goodneſſe, that his innocence</l>
               <l>Long ſince deſeru'd to bee remooued hence:</l>
               <l>Wherefore true Iuſtice plac'd Him neere the Throne</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18353:6"/>
               <l>In heauen of one in three, of three in one.</l>
               <l>His life was ſpotleſſe: as his ſickneſſe grew,</l>
               <l>So did his zeale and calmeneſſe: all is true</l>
               <l>In him, which Poets by hyperboly</l>
               <l>Giue their choyce friends to make their memory.</l>
               <l>Immortall. Like a thankefull ſtreame he ran</l>
               <l>To pay his debt vnto the Ocean.</l>
               <l>His Monuments of Learning were beſtow'd</l>
               <l>Where he had his. He paid what ere he ow'd;</l>
               <l>Obedience to his Parents, Loue to all,</l>
               <l>Repentance, death for's ſinnes in generall.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Vere lugentis Pietas.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>QVae Fata quondam cecinit Henricì, tibi</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Modò Muſa, magne luuenis, exequias parat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Documenta mors maiora nunquam virium</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dedit ſuarum, ſimile non poteſt malum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ruina ſimilis, Carolo ſuperſtite</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saluoque rege, &amp; integro cultu Dei,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Accidere nobis: lector iſtorum benè eſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si conualeſcat: deficit mihi ſpiritus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. I.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>REdde ô Depoſitum Patri petenti,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Redde ô Depoſitum diſerta ſedes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tanti non emo Literas, nec Antrum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et Phoebi Tripodas, Deumque totum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illum ſub dubij tepore ſenſus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et fuſcâ biuij trementis horâ</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Luctantem, toties Lare in Paterno</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Emerſiſſe, ſemel nec inde noſtro?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illum tendiculas manumque Fati</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prenſantis toties cauere poſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vt damni mora foeneraret ingens</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Huic aurae ſcelus, inuidumque nomen</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18353:7"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seruaret miſeris ruina Muſis?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nunc iras veteres palam fatentur,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſis ah nimis aſperae ſorores,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſis, irrita quòd Sepulchra reddunt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et fallunt tenebras ſilentis Vrnae.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I am fato cecidit Triumphus ingens,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non vulgare epulum rogum ſaginat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed Praenobile, quodque delicato</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reddat iam proceres ſapore vermes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cymbam nunc inopem roſis &amp; alga</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nauclerus Stygiae paludis ornat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ornat ſollicitus; magiſque ſudat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quam ſi nunc reduci foros pararet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeneae, Dominaeque nauiganti.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illo quot Veneres, Facetiaſque</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vernantes licuìt videre vultu?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quot pexo mulierculas in Ore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et quantos animo viros adulto?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vno non potuit iacere telo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virtus tam numeroſa; ſed tenello</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Centum pectore condidit ſagittas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fati certa lues: Character irae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dum veſtigia vulnerum fatetur</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Seu morbus fuerat, Pudoruè Morbi,)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crebris morſibus hinc &amp; hinc rubeſcit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abſumptum eſt iaculis repentè pectus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et poſses pharetram vocare metam;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non ſic foemina ſpinulis refertum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Puluillum iugulat, veneficaeque</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Humanas fodiunt acu figuras:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non tot vulnera, tot per omne corpus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Caeſar <hi>ſuſtinuit, quot ille ſolo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Senſit corde puer, Puerque ſpreuit</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18353:7"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ingens pectore, iamque vulnerato:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui quamuis puer, auſus est minantes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non pallere Deas, ferociamque</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oſtentare viri, tuamque</hi> Caeſar,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dum ſtratis operit pudicus ora</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Obnubitque ſinum! ferox, &amp; acer!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quem vinci puduit iubente Fato!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gulielmus Strode Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>SLeepe, ſweeteſt youth, in thy ſtill graue,</l>
               <l>Whom birth nor vertue could not ſaue,</l>
               <l>Nor louelineſſe nor youth could free,</l>
               <l>From this doome of mortality.</l>
               <l>Could we with teares thy life redeeme,</l>
               <l>Our eyes ſhould be a liuing ſtreame:</l>
               <l>Or elſe what would wee not contriue</l>
               <l>To giue, ſo heauen would thee repriue</l>
               <l>To older yeeres, and would thee ſaue</l>
               <l>Till old, thou might'ſt become a graue?</l>
               <l>Thou might'ſt depart then without wonder,</l>
               <l>When ſoule and body fall aſunder.</l>
               <l>But thou waſt louely, young, and wiſe,</l>
               <l>The comfort of our hopes and eyes;</l>
               <l>Could Death diſcerne thy parts, or ſee;</l>
               <l>Hee had enamored beene on thee:</l>
               <l>Thy beauty would force him forbeare</l>
               <l>His churliſh dart, and ſhead a teare;</l>
               <l>To ſee ſo faire an obiect ſtand,</l>
               <l>That loue and pitty could command;</l>
               <l>And force compaſſion in each one,</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18353:8"/>
               <l>That had or ſence, or paſſion.</l>
               <l>But thou waſt ripe for heauen, and wee</l>
               <l>Are left behind, to grieue for thee:</l>
               <l>Nor are we angry with that doome.</l>
               <l>Could wee weepe Amber, and entombe</l>
               <l>Thoſe louely Reliques, which might bleſſe</l>
               <l>Our ſorrow in thy happineſſe;</l>
               <l>That ſo our teares might thee embrace,</l>
               <l>And ſhrine thee in a louely place,</l>
               <l>So they vnto eternity</l>
               <l>Might both enbalme, and bury thee:</l>
               <l>Could we thus bleſſe our griefe, and thee,</l>
               <l>Wee ſhould weepe a glad Elegy.</l>
               <l>Had we ſuch comfort in our teares,</l>
               <l>We'd weepe the remnant of our yeres,</l>
               <l>To halfe redeeme thee, could wee ſaue</l>
               <l>Thy aſhes in ſo rich a graue.</l>
               <l>Though this is but a wiſhed gift,</l>
               <l>Yet griefe can make a louing ſhift,</l>
               <l>And know our loue can make a roome,</l>
               <l>As euerlaſting as this Tombe.</l>
               <l>In ſpight of death, wee will thee ſaue,</l>
               <l>Both from the fate of death, and graue:</l>
               <l>Thy loue ſhall find, though life's thus ſpent,</l>
               <l>In each mans heart a Monument.</l>
               <l>Thus wee'le preſerue thee, and contriue,</l>
               <l>Though dead, thou ſtill ſhalt bee aliue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>INuidia Fati, prima ſurrepta iuuenta,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic iacet Oxonij gloria, delitiae.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hunc populo indignum Muſae rapuere benigno</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amplexu, &amp; gremio depoſuere ſuo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Formam tota cohors Muſarum deperit, ambit:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18353:8"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeternumque aiunt, Hoc requieſce ſinu.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Annorum ſpondent faciles per ſaecula lapſus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dum rapit audaci mors inopina manu.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inuidiam hanc rident Muſae, tumuloque reponunt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carmineo, inuita &amp; viuere morte iubent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic quem mortalem Parcae inuidere Cmamaenis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeternum in noſtro carmine tutus erit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gulielmus Pickering, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>De morbo quo fratres vtri<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> laborabant.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Corpora tam ſimiles veſteſque habuere colores,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Corpora neſcires, an tunicata vides.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tam ſimiles vtrique dedit morbuſque figuras,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fratres vel morbo noueris eſſe duos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic morbi obſeruant habitus; conformia Fata</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si fuerant, fratres viuere vtroſque velint.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ioh. Euans Gen. Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>QVam fueras fratris morbo praepoſterus haeres,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vt viuat titulis poſthumus ille tuis?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iam nimius fueras Haeres, natura Parensis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Haeredem, fratris te tua Fata volunt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Credibile est mortem tum laſciuiſſe pharetra,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dum ſic alternas vibrat vtriſque minas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non errare poteſt dubiae manus impia mortis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dum pro fratre mori geſtit vterque prior.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dum ſic Bacchatur, Fatum eſt crudelius, alter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fratri morbus erat te perijſse ſuo.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Petr. Aſpley in Art. Bac. Equitis Aur. &amp; Turris Londini praefect. primogenitus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18353:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>TIs indeed, tis <hi>Stanhopes</hi> heire,</l>
               <l>Whoſe corps lye muffled on this Beere:</l>
               <l>(Which a pure loue, before it went,</l>
               <l>Ennobled more then his deſcent)</l>
               <l>But count his vertues, not his yeeres,</l>
               <l>Or gheſſe him by his Fathers teares,</l>
               <l>And then no Son or Heir's deſir'd,</l>
               <l>But th' whole Name and Race expir'd.</l>
               <l>Nor doth his death cauſe this our woe,</l>
               <l>(Death's our nature, not our foe)</l>
               <l>But that his life ſo ſoone being gone,</l>
               <l>Made him a gheſt, and not a ſonne;</l>
               <l>That hee ſnatcht in's minoritie</l>
               <l>Did rather looſe his life, then die.</l>
               <l>And now, his yeeres being vnderſtood</l>
               <l>To be ſo ſhort, and yet ſo good,</l>
               <l>Wee may diuide our paſſions ſo,</l>
               <l>That we may grieue, yet wonder too.</l>
               <l>His wit ſo ripe in youth ſo greene,</l>
               <l>Made him ancient at fifteene;</l>
               <l>And now you ſee his face no more,</l>
               <l>You would date him at threeſcore.</l>
               <l>But if you would memorials keepe</l>
               <l>Of this faire body lies aſleepe,</l>
               <l>That, looking on the toyes you weare,</l>
               <l>Though hee bee gone, you'd thinke him heere:</l>
               <l>Firſt know, you do this ſoule no grace,</l>
               <l>To catch his Ribbands, or his Lace,</l>
               <l>Or (as the Iewes did heretofore)</l>
               <l>To keepe his Earerings to adore:</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18353:9"/>
               <l>If for his memory you care,</l>
               <l>Weare his manners, not his haire.</l>
               <l>Thinke on him in his lateſt reſt,</l>
               <l>When death had ſpawnd vpon his breſt,</l>
               <l>And hurl'd thoſe deadly Atomes on,</l>
               <l>Enamel'd with corruption,</l>
               <l>How ſtill that harmeleſſe ſoule remaind</l>
               <l>Among ſo many ſpots, vnſtaind.</l>
               <l>O why was Fate ſo ſoone ſeuere,</l>
               <l>T'enchaſe thoſe vgly Rubies there?</l>
               <l>Nor will we mitigate the name,</l>
               <l>And call them Meaſels; for the ſame</l>
               <l>Were on the brothers body tride,</l>
               <l>Nor yet complain wee that hee died;</l>
               <l>Or how could Pin-duſt, caſt on's skin,</l>
               <l>Cauſe his death to enter in?</l>
               <l>Nor would then his Phyſicians skill</l>
               <l>Suffer ſuch Fleabites for to kill.</l>
               <l>No, this was fatall, twas his lot</l>
               <l>That from euery little ſpot,</l>
               <l>Should be drawne a line athwart</l>
               <l>To the Center of his heart.</l>
               <l>Or elſe God from ſome higher place,</l>
               <l>Seeded Manna on his face;</l>
               <l>And ſure tis ſo, or elſe hee'd ne're</l>
               <l>Haue put him in this Omer heere.</l>
               <l>Then let's now no more lament</l>
               <l>The dead, (whoſe life ſo wel was ſpent,</l>
               <l>That now for land, hee heauen doth ſhare,</l>
               <l>By his death a greater Heire)</l>
               <l>But our ſelues: for ſure tis worſe,</l>
               <l>To bee the Mourner then the Coarſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Lockey, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:18353:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>ERgone non auidos Muſarum expalluit hauſtus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ille puer, ſalſo ſtrenuus ore loqui?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergone non imas puduit redolere lucernas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vt damno afficeret mox grauiore Patrem?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Siccine ſelegit mors illum ex omnibus vnum?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illum, delitiae qui modo Patris erat?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſsimulare Patêr iam diſcas, vaetibi, Fata</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inuida ſi norînt, quis tibi charus erit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>LOoke on his body chequered o're with ſpots,</l>
               <l>Looke on his ſoule vntainted with ſuch blots.</l>
               <l>His purer part is frighted at each ſore,</l>
               <l>Two Twins were neuer ſo vnlike before.</l>
               <l>What wonder if a ſudden parting bee,</l>
               <l>Where thus the ſoule and body diſagree?</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edwardus Croke, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>ANd is our griefe ſo large? can't be confin'd</l>
               <l>To Place, to Time, but ſhowne to all mankind?</l>
               <l>Muſt wee remooue his Corps, and ſo conuey</l>
               <l>Our Thames to Trent, and weare another way</l>
               <l>With teares? to dally with our griefe, &amp; beare</l>
               <l>About our loſſe, as if wee playd with feare?</l>
               <l>Where doth this iourny after lifes iourny tend,</l>
               <l>This trauaile after death, this endleſſe end?</l>
               <l>Reſting he moues, and dead he ſtil doth rowle,</l>
               <l>As if his body went to ſeeke his ſoule:</l>
               <l>'Twas not becauſe we partners ſeeke of griefe,</l>
               <l>The greateſt ſorrowes ſeldome craue reliefe.</l>
               <l>Let's then diuide our woes, and let each care</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18353:10"/>
               <l>Enioy that want, and in ſuch ſorrow ſhare.</l>
               <l>Tis fit (though heere hee died) that countreys wombe</l>
               <l>That gaue him life, ſhould likewiſe bee his Tombe:</l>
               <l>To die, and to bee buried in one place,</l>
               <l>Beſeemes common mortality, his race</l>
               <l>Merits no captiue rites, then let our loſſe</l>
               <l>Bee as diffuſiue as his goodneſſe was.</l>
               <l>What though hee trace mortality, and dye?</l>
               <l>Death's a Refiner of Nobility:</l>
               <l>And in a freſher mould, and purer fire,</l>
               <l>Blazons him in a fairer Character.</l>
               <l>This were an honeſt comfort, if being dead,</l>
               <l>Our griefe could haue their obiect buried:</l>
               <l>If wee onely with our mem'ry did beare,</l>
               <l>And with thoſe eies alone to thinke him here.</l>
               <l>But loe, here's part of him, which doth extend</l>
               <l>His life beyond his life, nor doth death end</l>
               <l>Himſelfe, though halfe himſelfe, for now in this</l>
               <l>We both do view, although one whole we miſſe.</l>
               <l>Nor doe we here retaine a Light ſo cleare,</l>
               <l>As when two Suns pac'd in one Hemiſpheare,</l>
               <l>Nor doe Tyndarides diuided ſhine</l>
               <l>So bright, as when they both their Lights combine:</l>
               <l>When two are link't and parted, then wee may</l>
               <l>An obſcure twilight call it, and no day.</l>
               <l>Memorials of the good, and Pictures doe</l>
               <l>Reſtore our griefe, and make vs loue our woe.</l>
               <l>So when wee ſee his Brothers ſhape, theſe lips,</l>
               <l>Theſe eyes of his, theſe cheekes, that face, it ſtrips</l>
               <l>Vs of our ſence, and foorthwith makes vs frame,</l>
               <l>That tis no Brother, Picture, but the ſame:</l>
               <l>And writes his Name afreſh, leſt griefe ſhould dye:</l>
               <l>Each limbe of his ſpeakes his mortality.</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18353:11"/>
               <l>This is our ioy, our griefe, that wee requeſt</l>
               <l>Almoſt of that loue to bee diſpoſſeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His yeeres I neede not computate, ſince Fate</l>
               <l>His riper vertues, not his yeeres doth date,</l>
               <l>Which who ſo dares to number, muſt confeſſe</l>
               <l>Hee ſlanders, by commending happineſſe.</l>
               <l>But's richer ſoule wee muſt admire, not praiſe</l>
               <l>That groſer Heraldry deſpaires to blaze.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Adored Saint, or more, if more there bee</l>
               <l>Of thy bleſt Reliques onely knowne to thee;</l>
               <l>Wee doe confeſſe th'art gone, and yet our loſſe</l>
               <l>If told, is vnderualued, ſo groſſe,</l>
               <l>So young are our complaints, that wee lament</l>
               <l>In petty Notions, ſorrowes rudiment:</l>
               <l>Our infant teares yet knowes not all our woe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe wee knewe not all that was to growe</l>
               <l>In him, a graft all hope, but riper yeeres</l>
               <l>Shall teach vs how to parallell our teares,</l>
               <l>And ſo improoue wee may, (as hee did grow</l>
               <l>In vertue) dayly thriuing in our woe.</l>
               <l>Can then that Riuer which by thee doth ſlide,</l>
               <l>Bee ſo vnmindfull, not to bee full Tide,</l>
               <l>And not ore-flow his bounds? O be ſo good</l>
               <l>To ſaue a wonder, leſt wee force a flood;</l>
               <l>Swell thou <hi>(Meander</hi> ſtreames) let flow thy teares,</l>
               <l>Better proportioned to our fruitfull feares;</l>
               <l>Or let that Dog-ſtarre cauſe thee to bee ſpent,</l>
               <l>As t did his life, our eyes ſhall weepe a Trent,</l>
               <l>And make his Tombe an Iland, thou ſhalt bee</l>
               <l>(Shelford) more famous for mortality.</l>
               <l>And thou the Wel-ſpring, which with Arts didſt flow,</l>
               <l>(Bereaued Oxford) be a well of woe.</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18353:11"/>
               <l>Let Future times this firſt note learne of thee.</l>
               <l>Here dyed a <hi>Stanhope.</hi> Thus thou learn'd may bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVEe doe not here examine why</l>
               <l>His Tutor ſuffred him to die,</l>
               <l>As if his watchfulneſſe had ſlept:</l>
               <l>For ſure hee was by <hi>Argos</hi> kept,</l>
               <l>And had hee not a <hi>Stanhope</hi> beene,</l>
               <l>Hee might his Natures Tutor ſeeme:</l>
               <l>But wee queſtion that which forc't</l>
               <l>God and man to bee diuorc't.</l>
               <l>That firſt Queſtion, that Where, that Why,</l>
               <l>That ſentenc'd firſt our ſoules to dye.</l>
               <l>If fruit now haue that power of death,</l>
               <l>As in the child-hood of the earth,</l>
               <l>Which Fruit to cloake we Leaues put on,</l>
               <l>Cloth'd with our owne tranſgreſſion.</l>
               <l>No, know his ſoule ſo pure, ſo good,</l>
               <l>And how corruption it withſtood;</l>
               <l>That needed almoſt had his skinne</l>
               <l>Rather to bee baptiz'd then ſinne.</l>
               <l>Though Cherries ſowne in ſuch a place,</l>
               <l>That what hee ate, hee wore in's face,</l>
               <l>Yet euery twinkling ſpot did lye</l>
               <l>Like Starres, but in a fairer Skie;</l>
               <l>Such beauty might the Moone remoue,</l>
               <l>Sooner then <hi>Endymions</hi> loue.</l>
               <l>And from his kiſſe her light to come,</l>
               <l>Rather then from that common Sun.</l>
               <l>If then Meaſels ſpangled thus,</l>
               <l>Imbroidered his face no worſe;</l>
               <l>If his diſeaſe ſo modeſt bee,</l>
               <l>And bluſh at it's owne cruelty;</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18353:12"/>
               <l>Then what may his beauty claime,</l>
               <l>Whom his ſickeneſſe thus became;</l>
               <l>And in the twilight of his dayes,</l>
               <l>Chequ'red his countenance with Rayes,</l>
               <l>Preſaging like a rubyed night,</l>
               <l>The Sunne awak't to ſhine more bright?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If then our griefe bee not at height,</l>
               <l>Behold his Fathers ſorrowes weight,</l>
               <l>Whoſe heauy iourney wing'd with feares,</l>
               <l>Cauſ'd his body ſweat with teares,</l>
               <l>And each officious limbe turn'd eye,</l>
               <l>Claiming their duty for to cry:</l>
               <l>And well I thinke all eye was hee,</l>
               <l>That in a double night did ſee,</l>
               <l>Nor will I euer that approoue,</l>
               <l>When thus it ſees that blind is loue:</l>
               <l>For fatherly affection may,</l>
               <l>Though it bee night, create a day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now with an honeſt hereſie,</l>
               <l>I could renounce Philoſophy,</l>
               <l>That ſeeing thus their paſſions knit,</l>
               <l>His Father did his ſoule beget,</l>
               <l>And if it were not ſo, then why</l>
               <l>Did's Fathers Fate teach him to dye,</l>
               <l>And by his Propheticke death,</l>
               <l>Make him's Heire in's loſſe of breath:</l>
               <l>So that alone, which had the might</l>
               <l>To part them, did them co-vnite?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor doth goodneſſe ceaſe with breath,</l>
               <l>See liberality after death,</l>
               <l>Gilding each Pariſh as they fall,</l>
               <l>(For each place claimes his Funerall)</l>
               <l>Where he raines a ſiluer ſhowre,</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18353:12"/>
               <l>Making each Towne like <hi>Danaes</hi> Towre.</l>
               <l>Or as a ſnaile which neuer more</l>
               <l>Returnes the way ſh'ath gone before,</l>
               <l>Chriſtals the path where ſhee doth paſſe,</l>
               <l>To ſignifie there her way was.</l>
               <l>Nor any other Tombe ſhee'le haue</l>
               <l>But her ſhell, her houſe her graue:</l>
               <l>So will <hi>Stanhope</hi> no where lye,</l>
               <l>But where hee had's natiuity.</l>
               <l>Though Aegypt claimes hee died in her,</l>
               <l>Yet Canaan muſt his bones interre.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richardus Chaworth, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>IS <hi>Stanhope</hi> dead? and are our eyes yet dry?</l>
               <l>Can wee out-face our griefe ſo conſtantly?</l>
               <l>Doth not hard-hearted Athens yet lament,</l>
               <l>That is depriu'd of ſuch an Ornament,</l>
               <l>A Sonne and a <hi>Mecaenas?</hi> Can ſhee find</l>
               <l>One that deſeru'd ſo well that's left behind?</l>
               <l>Mourne then ſad Athens, and in memory</l>
               <l>Of ſuch ahopefull Sonne, weepe out an eye:</l>
               <l>Doe ſomething, that poſterity may know,</l>
               <l>So great a loſſe cannot bee ſmother'd ſo.</l>
               <l>And you ſad Brothers, whoſe yet weeping eyes</l>
               <l>Threaten a flood of teares, whoſe memories</l>
               <l>Are yet freſh-gauld with ſorrow, whoſe hearts weepe</l>
               <l>Channels of blood for teares, whoſe checkes yet keep</l>
               <l>The furrowed gutters where their ſorrow flowes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe foreheads are the enſignes of their woes,</l>
               <l>Make him a verſe or two, let him not dye,</l>
               <l>And periſh quite from the worlds memory;</l>
               <l>Hurle ſomething into feet, and let it runne</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18353:13"/>
               <l>Madding abroade, to tell what Death hath done.</l>
               <l>Had hee this entertainement when hee came</l>
               <l>To honour Athens? might not <hi>Stanhopes</hi> Name</l>
               <l>Haue priuiledg'd him from death? could Shelford giue</l>
               <l>Him to himſelfe? and ſend him heere to liue?</l>
               <l>And muſt wee giue him death? muſt Athens prooue</l>
               <l>A Step-mother, and quite forget to loue?</l>
               <l>Yet thus much let vs honour him, though dead,</l>
               <l>Let him bee honourably buried;</l>
               <l>Yet that's not all; wee muſt not leaue him thus,</l>
               <l>Our ſorrow muſt bee more ingenious.</l>
               <l>One that deſeru'd to liue ſo long as he,</l>
               <l>Muſt not bee haſten'd to his deſtiny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus farre his death hath brought him: let vs ſtriue</l>
               <l>To reinfomre him, that hee may reuiue,</l>
               <l>And thus much croſſe the Fates, that thus much durſt</l>
               <l>To make him liue, when they haue done their worſt.</l>
               <l>Let vs record his vertues, which deſeru'd</l>
               <l>To bee ingrauen in gold, or bee reſeru'd</l>
               <l>In truſty Caedar, which when wee are dead,</l>
               <l>Among our childrens children may bee read;</l>
               <l>Where ſome may ioy to heare them told, and ſome</l>
               <l>May liſpe them out as they were taught at home.</l>
               <l>They neede not feare miſ-reckoning, hee had all,</l>
               <l>And all hee thought a number too too ſmall.</l>
               <l>Hee was an heauen on earth, in whom combin'd</l>
               <l>His vertues like a Conſtellation ſhin'd:</l>
               <l>In which each ſtarre prickt with a iealous feare,</l>
               <l>Did ſtriue to bee the glory of his Spheare:</l>
               <l>His Noble birth ſhin'd like a Ruby ſet</l>
               <l>To bee the grace of a rich Cabbinet;</l>
               <l>His education ſhaddowing it o're,</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:18353:13"/>
               <l>So well becom'd it, that it ſhin'd the more.</l>
               <l>His pretty and ingenuous face did looke</l>
               <l>Like the good Title of an honeſt Booke:</l>
               <l>His comely ſhape, which did become him beſt,</l>
               <l>Look't like the Sanctuary of the reſt:</l>
               <l>As if the patterne were ſome Deity,</l>
               <l>Which Nature coppied his perfections by.</l>
               <l>Vertues amazed with a fond delight,</l>
               <l>Gazing and doting at ſo ſweet a ſight:</l>
               <l>At length with full embraces did oppreſſe</l>
               <l>This Microcoſme, or world of happineſſe.</l>
               <l>Where with an emulating induſtry,</l>
               <l>Each ſhewing an obſequious Piety,</l>
               <l>Labour'd to better Nature, and goe on</l>
               <l>With that rare work which nature had begun.</l>
               <l>His affable and willing Courteſy</l>
               <l>Claim'd vpper hand of his Nobility,</l>
               <l>He was right Noble, borne of <hi>Stanhopes</hi> blood,</l>
               <l>But was thrice Noble, being borne ſo good.</l>
               <l>His courteous ſalutings ſeem'd to bee</l>
               <l>Notable Emblemes of humility:</l>
               <l>His heart was like his eyes, which towr'd ſo high,</l>
               <l>They ſtoopt not to the lure of vanity.</l>
               <l>Doe yee not wonder yet? then ſtay and ſee</l>
               <l>His learning ballanc'd with his infancy;</l>
               <l>Marke but how young hee was, how ripe in wit,</l>
               <l>His learning him, and hee had honour'd it:</l>
               <l>Hee needes not Armes to ſhew his Anceſtry,</l>
               <l>That was ſo Noble by's owne Heraldry:</l>
               <l>Neither need Logicke prooue hee was a man,</l>
               <l>When he could proue as much as logicke can.</l>
               <l>Could hee bee idle, that with eaſie paines</l>
               <l>Summon'd each Coaſt, &amp; call'd them by their names?</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18353:14"/>
               <l>Wanted he knowledge, whoſe Minority</l>
               <l>Durſt be acquainted with Philoſophy?</l>
               <l>Speake, art thou yet ſo ſtupid, to deny</l>
               <l>That he was too good for Mortality?</l>
               <l>He was growne old in goodnes, and could ſee</l>
               <l>The way to heauen, euen in his Infancie.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henricus Humberſton, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Vpon the cuſtome to pay to euery Pariſh, through which the dead Corps is carried.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHy iſt you ſtop our rites, as though a Dearth</l>
               <l>Of Pence had made new ferry-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on earth?</l>
               <l>And iſt ſuch charges for to dye, that wee</l>
               <l>By Water and by Land too pay a Fee?</l>
               <l>Why with ſuch ſtrictneſſe, doe you aske your pay,</l>
               <l>As though you bargain'd for the Kings High-way?</l>
               <l>I thought at leaſt our Carkaſſe might haue bin</l>
               <l>Quiet in Death, in that our lateſt Inne.</l>
               <l>Or that naild Coffins, or vnwrapped Lead,</l>
               <l>From all vexation ſafe had kept the dead.</l>
               <l>Let him in peace walke to his ſilent Caue,</l>
               <l>To the long ſolemne progreſſe of his graue:</l>
               <l>Trouble not his Proceſſion: for ye</l>
               <l>Him this way wandring neuer more ſhall ſee.</l>
               <l>He comes not to poſſeſſe your grounds or lands,</l>
               <l>Or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n your Tenements to ſeaze his hands;</l>
               <l>He is no Court-meſſenger, to take in</l>
               <l>Lodgings or houſe-roome for the State or King:</l>
               <l>Hee's but's owne Harbinger to prouide roome,</l>
               <l>E'ne for a little earth, ſixe foote of Tombe:</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18353:14"/>
               <l>Then let him paſſe, vntroubled with thoſe feares,</l>
               <l>And wee will follow after with our teares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O let's wrap one teare vp, to ſhew his Hearſe,</l>
               <l>Hee cannot bee ſo ſoone forgot: a Verſe,</l>
               <l>Well ſpent, Embalmes him richer then the coſt</l>
               <l>Of precious oyntment on his body loſt:</l>
               <l>Which onely for the Wormes perfumes his fleſh,</l>
               <l>And makes it but more handſome rottenneſſe:</l>
               <l>But this doth quicken Fame, and this doth raiſe</l>
               <l>A volume of ſorrow for after-dayes,</l>
               <l>That men, ten Ages hence, may weepe to ſee</l>
               <l>Such hopefull Plants, ſuch thriuing grafts as hee,</l>
               <l>So young, and yet ſo full of age, ſo good,</l>
               <l>To feele vntimely blaſting in the bud.</l>
               <l>As though 'twere Natures pride to deale with vs,</l>
               <l>As Mothers with their froward Infants vſe,</l>
               <l>Who bribe them quiet with a coſtly Iemme,</l>
               <l>But being ſtill, doe ſteal't away agen.</l>
               <l>The world was peeuiſh, froward, till to light</l>
               <l>Was brought this rich, this high-priz'd Margarite;</l>
               <l>Which being ſeene, gaz'd on, and wondred at,</l>
               <l>Was reconuai'd to Heauen, its proper ſeat,</l>
               <l>Where Angels ware it, any bleſt powers it ſet</l>
               <l>In their owne truely-glorious Cabinet.</l>
               <l>No ſooner had we ſeene this Iemme, but ſee</l>
               <l>The want thereof, ſuch happineſſe haue wee,</l>
               <l>So bleſſed are we; O what greater ill,</l>
               <l>To haue had good, and not to haue it ſtill?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How we renew our griefe? how prone we bee</l>
               <l>To ſhead new teares, as often as we ſee</l>
               <l>Thy Fellow-Brother ſadly walke alone,</l>
               <l>Without a like-clad Brother, too well knowne?</l>
               <l>What pitty 'tis to part the Turtle Doue</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18353:15"/>
               <l>From his Mater to part two Twins? for in loue</l>
               <l>None elder was, one ſoule the ſtore-houſe was</l>
               <l>Of both affections, and though they paſſe</l>
               <l>For two, yet truſt me, I did then deſcry</l>
               <l>As the ſame ſoule in a ſeuer'd body.</l>
               <l>Hee that ſuruiues, takes vantage by thy fall,</l>
               <l>To ſhew his laſt loue to thy Funerall;</l>
               <l>To thy memory his beſt griefe to giue,</l>
               <l>And to thy Shrine a Votary to liue,</l>
               <l>To offer ſighs and ſobs, complaints and feaers,</l>
               <l>And ſweetly weepe foorth Elegiacke teares,</l>
               <l>To blame thy Phyſicke, &amp; to vexe their skill,</l>
               <l>Which is profoundly myſticall to kill.</l>
               <l>And then with paſſion to excuſe their part,</l>
               <l>And ſay the Cherries kill'd thee, not their Art:</l>
               <l>And truely wiſh that guilty curſed fruit,</l>
               <l>May with the Apples curſe, and figtrees ſuite.</l>
               <l>That their Sodom increaſe blacke aſhes bee</l>
               <l>Which more become a coffin, then a tree:</l>
               <l>That they ne're come to ripenes, but be ſnatcht</l>
               <l>Away as greene, as thou from him art catcht.</l>
               <l>Thus his diuided ſoule, with griefe and loue</l>
               <l>Striues ſtill for new, his firſt thoughts to remooue:</l>
               <l>So to thy fortunes although hee bee Heire,</l>
               <l>His heart and blacks alike ſad Emblemes are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But mourne no more, his ſoule was due long ſince,</l>
               <l>And now vnbody'd for the Angels Prince:</l>
               <l>The firſt borne Gods Heire is, reioyce hee's gone,</l>
               <l>For 'twas his iuſtice to make him his owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. Triplet, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18353:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>VVE that empty on thy Hearſe,</l>
               <l>Our paſſions in teares or verſe,</l>
               <l>Will not blame thy haſty Fate,</l>
               <l>Nor ſay thou didſt not fill thy date</l>
               <l>Of a iuſt age, leſt wee deny</l>
               <l>Thy vertue, her natiuity:</l>
               <l>And ſo by the vntimely Layes,</l>
               <l>Not Fate, but we abridge thy dayes.</l>
               <l>If wee ſearch thy lifes account,</l>
               <l>'Tis not to what thy yeeres amount;</l>
               <l>Nor calculated by thy youth,</l>
               <l>But by thy vertues riper growth;</l>
               <l>We iudge a Circles excellence,</l>
               <l>Not by the large Circumference,</l>
               <l>But as the compaſſe it doth grace,</l>
               <l>With an vndiſtorted pace.</l>
               <l>No leſſe of thy ſhort race wee ſay,</l>
               <l>It's drawne home the neerer way,</l>
               <l>Paſſing vntill it met thy Fate</l>
               <l>With an vnperuerted gate.</l>
               <l>For carried with thy grauity,</l>
               <l>What errour could it driue awry?</l>
               <l>No wonder 'tis, that oft wee know,</l>
               <l>A new prepoſt'rous childhood grow</l>
               <l>In ſuch, as vnder that age ſhake,</l>
               <l>Which their ſelues a burthen make:</l>
               <l>Let vs wonder now wee ſee</l>
               <l>In Childhood, ages conſtancy:</l>
               <l>And thinke hee not vntimely dyed,</l>
               <l>In whom wee ſaw this wonder tryed;</l>
               <l>Wee'le ſpare our paſſions, &amp; our teares:</l>
               <l>This hath made vp thy failing yeeres.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18353:16"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>VT poſsit cineri tanto par vrna parari,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et mole inducta nobilis vrna premi,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic Dirces opus eſt, feretro ſuccumbat alumnus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cuius non ſemel est ſylua ſecuta chelyni.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cantilletque melos, ad ſaxa cienda, canorum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnde tibi sterni forma ſupina poteſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nullus populeo, lachrymata cortice, myrrha.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Subtili coelo marmora ficta linet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vrceolis noſtris lachrymas fundemus, &amp; inde</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Coementum accipiet flebilis vrna ſuum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Fowler, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>MAiori ſuccumbit Atlas iam pondere coeli,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et queritur ſenſiſſe nimis, miſerique lacerti</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ceu tonitrus crepitant, illos dum turba tuarum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virtutum concreta premit, dum mente Gygantem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Suſtentant, &amp; naturae compendia noſtrae;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic habuit ſolus, quicquid poſſedimus omnes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>En quantum Eloquium frontis, ridentis ocelli</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Blanditiae quantae, toto via lactea vultu</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spirauit. Non eſt è vino lacte papillae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Linea coelestis, candore notabilis ipſo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His radijs facta eſt. Quam prodigioſa tumentis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Luxuria ingenij, ſtupefactos efficit omnes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inceſtatque fidem. Studio fallente laborem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Furtiuè fruitur, ſemper tantum artis honeſta</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arſit auaritia, &amp; quaerenti haec defuit illi.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diuinos artus macula dum fata profanant,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ecce Meduſaeo feſtinat praepete triſtis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sollicituſque Pater. Numen tibi nocte diurna</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Indulget, dictatque vias. Quas vertis in vndas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diluuiem meditans, Ioue iam nolente, ſecundam.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18353:16"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Contendit pro morte Pater, ſibi vendicat aeuo:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O quàm magnus amor, ſi haec ſit diſcordia ſola</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſcordes habuiſse metus: hic illius, ille</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Huius Fata timet: Quaedam est victoria Patris,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saepeque praemoritur: quaeſi ſollicitare petebat</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Christum etiam in coelis, vt ſaluum redderet illum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prodigio, ſic ſic iſtum valuiſſe deceret.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Io. Dawſon, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>De variolis, quibus infeſtus obijt, &amp; in morbum relapſu.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>CVm Puer, hoſce lues premeret vibicibus Artus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Placatiſque fores Stellio numinibus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non tulit illa ſuae natura pericula ſortis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et repulit morbi verſicoloris opus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conatus libuit modicos contemnere, donec</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſtitit, heu, nimios delituiſse dolos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Parthica fraus morbi (nimis heu tibi Barbarus hostis)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tela retro miſit, plus nocuitque fuga.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic vitae ſtrategema tuae tua Fata pararant:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Te viſae eſt Fatis vita paraſſe tuis)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Foelices animae, quarum conſortia coelum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ambit, vt haud pigeat compoſuiſſe dolos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conticet Ideaum iam tandem fabula raptum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Repperit Achetypum cum Ganymedis amor.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geo. Griffith, in Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>I Cannot weepe for griefe, in men wee prooue</l>
               <l>Teares to bee Embleames but of childrens loue:</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18353:17"/>
               <l>Nor is't but baſtard ſorrow which we ſhow,</l>
               <l>When we on Funerals Cakes and Wine beſtow</l>
               <l>More thoughts, than on the buried, then alone,</l>
               <l>When we not plumpe for teares, we truely mone.</l>
               <l>So truely mone I thee, who, ere thou died,</l>
               <l>At once wert Natures, and thy Fathers pride.</l>
               <l>Kings, Queenes, and Princes of their Comets haue</l>
               <l>As Tragicall fore-runners of their graue:</l>
               <l>The Sunne it ſelfe, as in the Weſt it ſtood</l>
               <l>Vſhring thy face, lookt like a globe of blood,</l>
               <l>Not two houres ere thou dyedſt; and they ſay,</l>
               <l>His frighted Orbe would faine haue run away,</l>
               <l>Wer't not hedg'd in with Planets, three and three,</l>
               <l>On either ſide, for feare't ſhould be too free:</l>
               <l>O that thy ſoule, like th' Sunne in his owne Spheare,</l>
               <l>Had ſtill remain'd; then friends, without a teare,</l>
               <l>Might both haue ſeene, and hug'd thee, then yet might</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Shelford</hi> haue enioy'd their light.</l>
               <l>But Fate preuents my wiſhes, and now ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioues</hi> Royall Bird, the ſoules firſt reſedy,</l>
               <l>Not naturally to heauen aſcending,</l>
               <l>But by Arts faigned miracle, pretending</l>
               <l>A better flight: thinke how the other three,</l>
               <l>Allyed in Name and Conſanguinity,</l>
               <l>All Heires deceas'd, doe gratulate this one,</l>
               <l>In making there a Conſtellation,</l>
               <l>Like to <hi>Deltoton,</hi> which before might be</l>
               <l>Th'vnhappy Dog-ſtarre, 'cauſe there was but three.</l>
               <l>But as from <hi>Phoenix</hi> aſhes ſprings another,</l>
               <l>So out of thine an Heire, a younger Brother.</l>
               <l>But what's the comfort, when each Chaire &amp; Board,</l>
               <l>Like breathing Ghoſts, cry out their former Lord?</l>
               <l>If that for freer Ayre, he chance to walke</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18353:17"/>
               <l>Amongſt the curled wood, trees ſeeme to ſtalke.</l>
               <l>Each thing renewes his brothers memory,</l>
               <l>Or ſeemes his brother: If the ſtreames thereby</l>
               <l>Whiſper, hee thinkes they call him, ſtraightway feares</l>
               <l>And ſtriues to make a greater flood with teares:</l>
               <l>Perhaps the harmeleſſe flowres doe kiſſe his feete,</l>
               <l>Hee thinkes they mocke him, goes to th' open ſtreete,</l>
               <l>Where as hee walkes, beleeues each tongue and eye</l>
               <l>To ſpeake and looke his Brothers deſtiny.</l>
               <l>A Lethargie's on mee, nor can I write</l>
               <l>Whats Poet-like, while I conceiue this ſpite</l>
               <l>Of vniuſt Fortune, yet I ceaſe to brawle:</l>
               <l>A Satyre ill becomes a Funerall.</l>
               <l>If euer it did thine, the Poets braine</l>
               <l>Could ne're inuent ſuch a malignant ſtraine</l>
               <l>As fortune acts on thee, while thou preuent</l>
               <l>The Dog-dayes Phyſicke in deaths puniſhment:</l>
               <l>Thy face may rebeget in th' Mothers Wombe,</l>
               <l>A Monſter fram'd of griefe, whoſe liuing Tombe</l>
               <l>Shall bee the hearts of all that doe lament</l>
               <l>To ſee this Coffin, this Heires Tenement.</l>
               <l>I dare not ceaſe, leſt iudg'd by my owne feares,</l>
               <l>To bee as thrifty of my lines as teares;</l>
               <l>Yet who reſpects them, ſtones doe ſweat and weepe</l>
               <l>Other mens ſorrowes, but when thoſe that ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Awake and know neglect of friends, they then</l>
               <l>Will gratifie more Marble ſtones then men.</l>
               <l>But feare not thou, hee that ſhall euer ſee</l>
               <l>Thy Brothers ſhaddow, ſure will thinke it thee:</l>
               <l>Thou liueſt in him though dead, and as thou dyed,</l>
               <l>Thou ſeemeſt to dye in ieſt, ſo ſweetly lyed</l>
               <l>Each colour in his owne place, fear'd to part</l>
               <l>Thinking thou imitat'ſt a Players Art.</l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:18353:18"/>
               <l>But now they're vaniſht, yet thou art not farre,</l>
               <l>A Planet here, aboue a fixed Starre.</l>
               <l>Thou, though an Heire, wert but an earthly clod,</l>
               <l>Yet Death hath made thee more; an Heire with God.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Motershead, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>TErra, &amp; ſepulchrum, funus, &amp; lachrymaebreues,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et complementum quod<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> plebeiae necis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Procul recedant; fortis et doctus dolor</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Emanet oculis, ſpiret &amp; muſam niſi</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Totus virilis, plenus &amp; dignus Deo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeternitati, noſter, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vmbraepiae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Litet Poeta, carminis vires ſui</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hinc mutuetur hinc, quibus vitam dedit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ipſum cadauer (melius ah daret ſibi)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sumus argumento docti, at &amp; nobis tamen</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hoc iſtud aufers; victor at quare procul</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Frater recedit? Mors in hunc vires ſuas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Experta, victa eſt, igitur in fratrem ruens</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pudore rubuit, &amp; verecundo dolo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Intus recedens, occupat cordis ſinum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et ſe fateri metuit; hinc audax foras</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egreſſus ipſe eſt, addit &amp; morbo ſuo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ceraſi ruborem, (cuius inſidias</hi> ADAM</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non ipſe fugeret) mortis &amp; miro modo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rubore nimto pallet ah tandem nimis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et ipſe palles, ſpiritus tanquam duos</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Animaret vnus, incipis primùm mori,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Doceſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> natum, qui patrizauit nimis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nimium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> monstrat indolem promptam ſuam,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:18353:18"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leto vel ipſo, gaudet &amp; diſcens mori.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Campana magna ſonuit &amp; nato, &amp; tibi,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amboſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gemuit ipſa ſecretò tamen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Horam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Nonam facta iam fallax boat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mortem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pariter, timuit hanc palam loqui.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dormite tandem, non Magiſtratus opus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Autoritate eſt, ambulat tantum dolor;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turgenſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> factus quis<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iam lachrymis ſuis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inebriatur, gemitus Epicuros facit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Solare iam te, fortiter tandem gemas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Solare coniugem, ecce qui vicit necem;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spes germinantes, &amp; reuiuentes duos</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vno videbis, corpore &amp; mentem gerens</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Geminatam in vno, fiet Henricus tibi</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Frater<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; ipſe, ceraſa tam fratri mala</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Labris in ipſis geſtat, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eius poteſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Imago mortis eſſe, qui vitae volet.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Epitaphium.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>HOc ſitus in tumulo eſt, pro quo lapis inſitus illo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Marmoris in lachrymas quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſolutus erit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Canus doctrinâ eſt, annis quam paruus! at iſtos</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quos natura negat tradidit ipſe ſibi.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nobilitans ſtirpem virtutum ſoenore, &amp; haeres</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Patris opum merito, qui pietatis erat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Occidit Oxonij, iacet hìc; terrae iſta gemiſcit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ereptum, quem ſic haec habuiſſe dolet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Debuit at luctus tam publicus eſse, iacere</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vno non poterat tanta querela loco.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Poſuit officij ergò</hi> Geor. Aglionby, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18353:19"/>
            <head>Vpon the vntimely death of the Right Noble Gentleman, Maſter <hi>Iohn Stanhope,</hi> Sonne and Heire to the Right Honourable <hi>Philip</hi> Lord <hi>Stanhope,</hi> Baron of <hi>Shelford.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SO great, ſo good, and yet ſo ſoone to dye?</l>
               <l>Sure, there was Godhead in's mortality,</l>
               <l>Of which the greedy heauens, enuying the earth,</l>
               <l>Snatcht to themſelues, leauing to vs a dearth</l>
               <l>Of goodneſſe, of vertue a meere penury;</l>
               <l>Blaſting the hope of an vnſtain'd family:</l>
               <l>Vnſtain'd, and free from ſuch grand villanies</l>
               <l>Which poiſon Honour, hee knew none of theſe</l>
               <l>Hereditary euils, and crimes which ſome</l>
               <l>As 'twere eſſentiall bring, euen from their wombe:</l>
               <l>But like to Demi-gods, all his Progeny</l>
               <l>Were good, and honeſt, innocent as hee:</l>
               <l>Hee, whoſe refined ſoule goodneſſe alone</l>
               <l>Ingroſt, clayming each vertue as his owne:</l>
               <l>Who with his other-ſelfe did ſtill appeare,</l>
               <l>Like to the Twins in heauen, and ſhone as cleare;</l>
               <l>No cloudy vice did e're eclipſe their light,</l>
               <l>They ſhone by day as th' other doe by night;</l>
               <l>And as they were, ſo did they Brothers proue,</l>
               <l>But not ſo much by Nature, as by Loue.</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſharpeſt anger ne're did mooue their blood;</l>
               <l>The ſtrife was onely which ſhould bee moſt good:</l>
               <l>Thus curious Nature ſtroue to ſhew her Art</l>
               <l>In theſe, giuing two bodies, but one heart.</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18353:19"/>
               <l>And ſuch an heart which each would ſacrifice,</l>
               <l>To dry the teares flowing from eithers eyes.</l>
               <l>Mee thinks I ſee when one diſeaſed lay,</l>
               <l>The others loue ſteale the diſeaſe away;</l>
               <l>And when his ſickeneſſe broke foorth of the skinne,</l>
               <l>With what reſolued loue hee ſtrooke it in,</l>
               <l>To free his Brother, and to bee ſure at laſt</l>
               <l>Rather then faile, hee'd periſh by the taſte</l>
               <l>Of fruit enuy'ng his cheekes, ſeeming to bee</l>
               <l>Th' vnhappy fruit of a forbidden tree.</l>
               <l>By which perceiuing death to haſten on,</l>
               <l>Hee breath'd out prayers with ſuch deuotion,</l>
               <l>That his religious Father doubtfull ſtood,</l>
               <l>If hee ſhould liue, or die, hee died ſo good.</l>
               <l>Whoſe bleſt departure prou'd him thus to bee,</l>
               <l>Full ripe for heauen in his infancy.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Row. Crosbey, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>TO tell our loſſe, ſo well to each man knowne,</l>
               <l>Were to lament our ſelues, not him that's gone:</l>
               <l>That were to cry out helpe to thoſe that lye</l>
               <l>By the ſame griefe dead to eternity.</l>
               <l>Alas! that men may fully vnderſtand</l>
               <l>Whom 'tis they loſe, requires thy braine, thy hand.</l>
               <l>But ſince th' art gone, and wee cannot relate</l>
               <l>Thy worth ſo liuely, yet let's imitate</l>
               <l>Thy life, by one that's left vs, for no other</l>
               <l>So perfect is, as thou art in thy Brother.</l>
               <l>For what thing was it, thou enioyd'ſt aliue,</l>
               <l>That thou didſt not impart or wholy giue</l>
               <l>Vnto thy Brother, hee againe as true</l>
               <l>Thought himſelf then moſt bleſt, when moſt like you.</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18353:20"/>
               <l>And of this loue there euer was ſuch ſhew,</l>
               <l>As it was thought they would haue both dy'd too.</l>
               <l>Perchance he ate the Cherries, for to make</l>
               <l>Himſelfe red-colour'd for his brothers ſake.</l>
               <l>But O vnhappy triall! they did proue</l>
               <l>Too crafty farre, for his well-meaning loue.</l>
               <l>Did we not loſe enough when <hi>Adam</hi> fell</l>
               <l>By thee, curſt Fruit? but thou muſt longer ſtill</l>
               <l>Produce our miſeries, and when w'are beſt,</l>
               <l>By tempting one muſt murther all the reſt.</l>
               <l>Was he too good for Earth, &amp; did heau'n call</l>
               <l>To haue him there, ſo that he needs muſt fall?</l>
               <l>If ſo, tis well; for it was equity,</l>
               <l>Mankind and hee by the ſame Fate ſhould dye.</l>
               <l>But though th' art dead, thy memorie ſuruiues,</l>
               <l>And thy good deeds ſhall out-laſt others liues.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guliel. Buckner, Art. Bac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>DEpoſitum</hi> (Stanhope) <hi>tuum (memorande) ſupremum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ipſe pater patriâ concumulauit humo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nec licuit feretro nobis ſuſpendere Carmen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nec Trentae lachrymas annumerare tuo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nostra tamen ſimiles lacrymarum Nympha lacunas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hauriet, &amp; Trentâ non minor Iſis erit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>WEepe, weepe, your ſorrowes are well paid,</l>
               <l>'Tis a <hi>Stanhope</hi> here is laid,</l>
               <l>You that ſee this Monument,</l>
               <l>And cannot at this ſight lament,</l>
               <l>The conſcious Marble will you ſhow,</l>
               <l>How to diſcharge your comely woe.</l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:18353:20"/>
               <l>Either you may th' occaſion ſit,</l>
               <l>By melting into teares like it:</l>
               <l>Or if you puniſh nor your eye,</l>
               <l>By weeping, cauſe it fatally</l>
               <l>Behold his Tombe, then may you mone,</l>
               <l>By ſtanding ſtupid, like the ſtone.</l>
               <l>Yet both theſe ſorrowes are well paid,</l>
               <l>'Tis a <hi>Stanhope</hi> here is laid.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guli. Treſhans, Equitis Aurat. Filius.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>IMmitis properare necem Libitina, potir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dum tanto exoptat coniuge, fata iubet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spiritus, ingenium, genius, decor oris, &amp; ortûs</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stemmata quem celebrant, aemula fatae prema <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Indole maturum flos indolis abſtulit, illum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dum numeraet laudes, quis negat eſſe ſenem?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non aeui breuitate fuit fraudata tropaeis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gloria, cum fuerit copia nulla nouis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laude viget, cuius fraterna videtur imago</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Accipere &amp; parili reddere fata vice.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>In Canem coeleſtem: eò quòd circa initium dierum Canicularium mortuus ſit.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>LEge nimis durâ funebria iuſta referre</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Icarij cogis feruida ſtella canis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Icaria peiora precor tibi fata ruina,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dùm tua ſic lachrymas ſorbet anhela ſitis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Betrus Tryon, Armig. Fil. nat. max.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:18353:21"/>
            <head>In Variolarum luem qua interijt.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>HOc Iuuemem placido decus immortale Sepulchro</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſpice, qui viuens immaculatus erat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dixiſſem ſi non fera Mors, morbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> peroſi</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Polluerant, moriens immaculatus erat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ah Laethi crudele genus, cum tetrica vultus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abſtulit, &amp; tenero ſaeuit in ore lues!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dulcia deformes ederunt oſcula morbi,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nec data ſunt auido pura labella rogo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tam celeri ſi ſaeua gradu ventura fuiſſent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nonne alia poterant fata venire via?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed Mors ſaeua decus properauit perdere vultus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ne poſset duras flectere forma Deas.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'TIs not Nobility that is of force,</l>
               <l>To ſtop the Progreſſe of this Tyrants courſe;</l>
               <l>Nor mortall can vnto himſelfe aſſume</l>
               <l>A ſparke of time, when Fate hath paſt her doome.</l>
               <l>So fraile are all Earths momentary things;</l>
               <l>That Death a Tribute claimes of greateſt Kings:</l>
               <l>But Death hath had her pay, and he his Crowne,</l>
               <l>Where neither Death can ſtrike, nor Fate can frown.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gul. Pennyman Armig. filius natu max. Ex Aede Chriſti.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>WErt not that dayly ſpectacles deny</l>
               <l>A difference betweene Nobility</l>
               <l>And other Pigmy Mortals, good and bad,</l>
               <l>The old and young, we iuſt occaſion had,</l>
               <l>Of admiration, when we doe behold</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18353:21"/>
               <l>Thee ſo good, young, and noble, vnder mould.</l>
               <l>But when the Graues and Sepulchres we view,</l>
               <l>We turne our admiration from you,</l>
               <l>Not wondring that a life ſo ſhort you led,</l>
               <l>But that our ſelues haue ſpun ſo large a thred</l>
               <l>Of our Mortality, when all places ſee</l>
               <l>Some dye continually; ſo that we</l>
               <l>Need draw our neuer-diſcontinued teares</l>
               <l>Vnto the Period of our lateſt yeeres.</l>
               <l>Here one fall's ſicke, and dyes, &amp; there another;</l>
               <l>Griefe for whoſe death, killeth, perhaps, his Brother,</l>
               <l>Father, or Mother: ſo it far'd with thee:</l>
               <l>For not thou onely, but a Family</l>
               <l>Did ſeeme in thee to die, for loe, thy Father,</l>
               <l>Secure of any worſe miſhap, had rather</l>
               <l>Suffer himſelfe ſome perill, than that death</l>
               <l>Before his comming, ſhould cloze vp thy breath.</l>
               <l>He comes, and iourneying thrice with humble knee</l>
               <l>Fall's to the Earth, yet being vtterly</l>
               <l>Inſenſible of this, through the great fire,</l>
               <l>Kindled by Loue, obtaineth his deſire.</l>
               <l>Thy Mother, fearing that thy houre was come,</l>
               <l>Striues to bring forth another in thy roome;</l>
               <l>And ſo with motherly compaſſion, loth</l>
               <l>To loſe the one, endangereth you both.</l>
               <l>Thy Brother of thy Fortune aemulous,</l>
               <l>Striues to preuent thee, whoſe ingenuous</l>
               <l>Loue and good-will to thee did then appeare,</l>
               <l>When thy laſt houre did ſhew he held thee deare.</l>
               <l>He faine to heauen would thy fore-runner bee,</l>
               <l>And there prouide place for himſelfe and thee.</l>
               <l>Wherefore he often offers willingly,</l>
               <l>Ranſome to pay for thy deliuery;</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18353:22"/>
               <l>And on condition thou maiſt here remaine,</l>
               <l>Dyes often, but deny'd, reuiues againe</l>
               <l>To his great griefe; at laſt, when nought would doe,</l>
               <l>Cryes out, and ſaies, Shall we be parted too?</l>
               <l>Tis true, you muſt a while, yet weepe no more,</l>
               <l>Since all your teares will not his life reſtore:</l>
               <l>Then ſince your weeping can't recall him gone,</l>
               <l>Waile not his death, ſeeke to preuent your owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Ad defuncti fratrem.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>DEfunctus foret ipſe ſibi tantae indolis haeres.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si poſsent iuſtae flectere fata preces.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed Natura negat: cui munera tanta relinquet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cùm nuda Elyſios vmbra pererret agros?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deuouet haec fratri: hunc haeredem ex aſse reliquit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quem ſocium tantae Nobilitatis habet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Viue tibi &amp; fratri, duplicem ſortitus honorem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Siſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> haeres illi moribus ingenio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thomas Ballowe, Alumnus.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>AN Heire, and dead? muſt ſome erected Tombe</l>
               <l>Cloze in the bowels of an earthly wombe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stanhopes</hi> great Heire? muſt it a Trophy bee</l>
               <l>Of his deceaſe? boaſt we in miſery?</l>
               <l>Are theſe the Lands that he was borne vnto?</l>
               <l>To lye dead in ſome <hi>Ephrons</hi> Field of woe?</l>
               <l>O tell me, Death, why is he turn'd to duſt?</l>
               <l>Wilt thou plead Fates decree, and cry, He muſt?</l>
               <l>Is thy beſt reaſon a neceſſity,</l>
               <l>Or grounded Maxime in Philoſophy?</l>
               <l>He was not old, for age he did not dye,</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18353:22"/>
               <l>Nor was the onely cauſe Mortality:</l>
               <l>This was the chiefeſt reaſon he deceaſt,</l>
               <l>Thy hunger was ingenuous, and to feaſt</l>
               <l>Was thy deſire, thou't not picke the bone</l>
               <l>Of ſome Anatomy or Skeleton:</l>
               <l>As for a Carkaſſe hanging in the Ayre,</l>
               <l>Halfe eaten vp by Time, thou doſt not care.</l>
               <l>The Wormes are Epicures, whoſe enuious ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Deuoures that Carkaſſe that had giuen them life;</l>
               <l>Nor can I blame them that they ſo doe eate,</l>
               <l>Though hee's a Courſe, yet is he dainty meat.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Eduard. Price, Alumnus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>I Thinke it is a policie in Death,</l>
               <l>To take the young, and ſpare the aged breath.</l>
               <l>Nature's the bane of old men; Times decree</l>
               <l>Sends them a packing; Death, they need not Thee;</l>
               <l>Thou onely ſeru'ſt to crop our tender yeeres,</l>
               <l>To draw from Parents eyes abortiue teares;</l>
               <l>Thou letſt them liue, their children tak'ſt away,</l>
               <l>Knowing that ſorrow will be their decay;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Death, pale, enuious Death! how could'ſt thou find</l>
               <l>Out the ſweet picture of ſo pure a mind?</l>
               <l>Me thinkes, although thy bloudy Dart were ſteel'd</l>
               <l>With thy ſad purpoſe; yet it muſt needs yeeld,</l>
               <l>To ſee the Father melting into teares,</l>
               <l>His ſad acquaintance, and his Brothers feares;</l>
               <l>Who ſent as many ſighes vnto the Pole,</l>
               <l>As might haue made, or elſe excus'd a ſoule.</l>
               <l>The Roome mournd where he lay, the weeping ſtones</l>
               <l>Ioyn'd with his friends in their relenting mones.</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18353:23"/>
               <l>Death migt haue well miſtaken, being ſent</l>
               <l>For one, to ſee ſo many that wayes bent;</l>
               <l>The Father three times offerd to haue payd</l>
               <l>Him-ſelfe for his Sonnes ranſome; had Death ſtayd</l>
               <l>His haſty hand, hee had found many more</l>
               <l>That had bin fitter to haue payd this ſcore.</l>
               <l>Alas, he was but in the bloſſom yet</l>
               <l>Of tender yeeres, though aged for his wit:</l>
               <l>Hee had ſome inſight into euery Art,</l>
               <l>That to <hi>Nobility</hi> might adde a part:</l>
               <l>His Parents reapt as much ioy from his ſpring,</l>
               <l>As many childrens Harueſt home doth bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But hee is fled away to paſſe the time</l>
               <l>Hee ow'd to vs, in a farre better Clime:</l>
               <l>There ſhall his Summer and his Harueſt bee,</l>
               <l>Where hee ſhall neuer any Winter ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, Parents, grieue no more; for he's in ioy;</l>
               <l>Doubt not; wipe yours; his teares are wip't away.</l>
               <l>Death tells mee, he was old enough to die,</l>
               <l>And young enough to liue eternally.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geruaſe Warmſtrey, Alumnus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>WHat fatall booke is this, which doth declare,</l>
               <l>That Noble <hi>Stanhop's</hi> houſe has loſt her heyre?</l>
               <l>A Sermon preach'd at <hi>Shelford!</hi> ah, tisſo,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stanhope</hi> is layd in Earth, theſe lines of woe,</l>
               <l>Demonſtrate he is dead: yet ſtay, wer't he,</l>
               <l>Oxford would put on ſorrowes liuery,</l>
               <l>Each Colledge mourne in aſhes, euery Hall</l>
               <l>Looke like the Embleme of a Funerall.</l>
               <l>Chriſt-church would ſink in ruine, were he gon,</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:18353:23"/>
               <l>On whom ſhee built her hopes foundation.</l>
               <l>Dulneſſe has ſeaz'd vpon me: can I reade</l>
               <l>That vertue's ſlaine, yet iudge not <hi>Stanhope</hi> dead?</l>
               <l>Betweene which two there was ſuch league, that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Could not ſubſiſt, the other beeing gon.</l>
               <l>In Churches why ſhould Death triumph, and bee</l>
               <l>Hanging vp Banners of her victory?</l>
               <l>What ſiege of Honour has ſhee won? Is't all,</l>
               <l>That ſhee has payd to Fate one Funerall?</l>
               <l>And that of feeble youth? yong <hi>Stanhope</hi> dyes,</l>
               <l>'Cauſe elſe ſhee knowes not where to tyrannize.</l>
               <l>It had beene Iuſtice, if ſome hoary head</l>
               <l>Had felt this deadly dart and periſhed.</l>
               <l>To bee vniuſt, is Death's iuſt attribute:</l>
               <l>For ſhee did murder him, not execute.</l>
               <l>But why ſhould wee her murders thus relate?</l>
               <l>Death's but the Executioner of Fate.</l>
               <l>Fate was to blame, whoſe too too greedy hand</l>
               <l>Did breake his thred of life, as loth to ſtand</l>
               <l>The leiſure for to cut it with her ſheeres,</l>
               <l>And ſo at once rob'd him of many yeeres.</l>
               <l>This is not all: his theft's farre greater yet,</l>
               <l>In robbing him, Fate rob'd vs all of wit.</l>
               <l>For <hi>Stanhope</hi> might haue liu'd a worke to raiſe,</l>
               <l>Which mought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Sydney's</hi> Temples pluck the Bayes,</l>
               <l>At leaſt haue equall'd him: ſuch hopes his braine</l>
               <l>Did promiſe to the world to bring againe.</l>
               <l>But wee haue loſt him: ſtrangers which but heare</l>
               <l>How good he was, are forc't to ſhead a teare;</l>
               <l>Well may his Father ſay, hee is vndone,</l>
               <l>Hee onely knew the worth of ſuch a Sonne:</l>
               <l>Let others thinke it ſtrange that griefe ſhould bee,</l>
               <l>As bold as death to worke a Tragedy;</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18353:24"/>
               <l>Thrice did his Father ſound, as if his Ghoſt</l>
               <l>Would take a Farewell of his ſon that's loſt;</l>
               <l>Yet wher's your wonder here? at ſuch a ſight</l>
               <l>I would not think it ſtrange to dy outright.</l>
               <l>So would hee, but one Death cannot ſuffice</l>
               <l>T' expreſſe his griefe, therefore hee after dyes,</l>
               <l>And could his ſorrowe quit his ſon from Death,</l>
               <l>Hee'd neuer leaue to grieue, whilſt he had breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Will. Hemmings, Alumnus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>TRiſte onus Hexaphori, moeſtae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Epicedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> turbae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inuitant lachrymas ore madente pias;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Occidit alma Hebe, patris ſpes, gloria fratrum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui partu primus, funere primus erat:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vendicat hanc Natura, hanc moeſta Academia prolem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuam petit hanc, Nobilitas<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuam,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurea cum moeſca certat numeroſa Cupreſso,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charta iſtos cineres, et leuis vrna petunt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed de virgineo ne ſit diſcordia vultu,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mors citiùs praedam vendicat atra ſuam:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Igne crepent gemmae, Domini nocteſcit ocellus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Huic gemmae nuſquam gemma ſuperſtes erit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pingues, quos tantùm capiti modò ſparſit, odores</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iam caput, et plantas, corpus, et omne linant,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed tamen vnguento meliori funera lauit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dum ſoluit nimijs imbribus ora parens,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At toti lachrymae non ſuffecêre dolori;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pars erat in vultu; plus tamen intùs erat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quid miſerande Pater langues, animo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> liqueſcis?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cur fugit exanimis, membra ſupina cruor?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Siſte Pater gemitus, et vitae parce ruenti,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vitam non ſatis eſt huic tribuiſse ſemel?</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:18353:24"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pace tuâ valeant manes, permitte quietem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et praeter famam, murmura nulla ſonent;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Manibus Auguſtis non pandit Cerberus aulam,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iam canis aethereus regnat, &amp; astra parat.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In Eundem.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HIc &amp; ſplendidius decus Parentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Orta &amp; ſtemmate nobili propago,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Funestum poſuit citò cadauer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et compagine ſpiritus ſoluta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Languentis malè corporis fauillae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Extincta eſt. Lachrymas mouent ſorores</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et moestae Tragico ſonant boatu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dum Parcea indociles fauore flecti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Primae ſtamina diſſecant iuuentae:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quis non exequijs liqueſcat istis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et fati ſcelus improbet ſeueri?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed fundant Tetricae minas ſorores,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non condet Libitina ſaeua Famam;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vita perfruitur beatiori,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Extento<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> diu ſuperstes aeuo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vitam artis trahit, &amp; ſepulchra ridet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O pectus iuuenis Vale quietum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Solennes feretri rogos ſuperbi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dum plaudit famulante muſa cantu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et coetus iuuenûm modeſtiorum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O ſit terra tibi leuis. (Precamur)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Terrae tam leuis antè, qui fuisti.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Franciſcus Minne, Alumnus.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:18353:25"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>ANne ego te Iuuenem</hi> (Stanhope) <hi>putabo Senemue?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cuius verna dies, gloria cana fuit!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cuius &amp; in decimâ vix quintâ aeſtate ſenectus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Imperat, &amp; puerum non puerum eſſe ſinit?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic non iuſtus eras, non fortis, doctus ad Annos:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed potuit virtus praecipitare dies;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non data longa tibi eſt, facta eſt longiſsima vita:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nec viuendo breuis, ſed moriendo fuit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohannes Donne, Alumnus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>NObilis at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſagax, properae virtutis alumnus;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et patris, &amp; patriae gloria prima ſuae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Occidit impubis; raptus trieteride quinta;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eheu, quàm Parcas iam rapuiſſe pudet!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vidêre vt multa canum virtute ſorores,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crediderant, viridis qui fuit, eſse ſenem.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>DEATH; alas, could none but hee</l>
               <l>Suffice thy greedy Tyranny?</l>
               <l>Wel thou knowſt that thouſands more</l>
               <l>Long haue run vpon thy ſcore;</l>
               <l>And with all humility,</l>
               <l>Yeeld themſelues as due a fee.</l>
               <l>Thy ſubtile cruelty is ſpide,</l>
               <l>Whileſt in one a thouſand dy'de:</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou tane <hi>Achilles</hi> Dart,</l>
               <l>Strucke, and then releas'd that ſmart;</l>
               <l>Thou hadſt done well: Once or twice</l>
               <l>It was thy ſport to let him riſe</l>
               <l>Out of his Bed: Now he ſtray'd</l>
               <l>Too farre with thee, now he ſtay'd.</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18353:25"/>
               <l>So <hi>Apollo</hi> ſlew his friend</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hyacinthe</hi> againſt his minde,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt the Quoit that he had thrown,</l>
               <l>Smote his gentle Play-mate downe.</l>
               <l>Grieue not then for him that's gone,</l>
               <l>See; Death's ſorry for what's done:</l>
               <l>Let no cryes oppreſſe your eares,</l>
               <l>Dry, O dry diſtilling teares;</l>
               <l>What though honour, vertue, grace,</l>
               <l>Though Nobilty of race,</l>
               <l>By the fatall Dart doth lie</l>
               <l>Subiect to Mortality?</l>
               <l>Let it not torment your minde</l>
               <l>See the Picture's left behinde:</l>
               <l>His Brother, modeſt, mild, as hee,</l>
               <l>Doth in vertue moſt agree.</l>
               <l>Aske not for them both together,</l>
               <l>This alone may paſſe for either.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Martinus Tynley, Alumnus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>HEere, though his ſpotleſſe ſpan-long life be ſpent,</l>
               <l>Are ſilent ſteps to ſhew where goodneſſe went.</l>
               <l>Nature did in ſuch rare compleatneſſe make him,</l>
               <l>To ſhew her Arte, and ſo away did take him.</l>
               <l>For he was onely to vs wretches lent</l>
               <l>For a ſhort time, to be our Preſident.</l>
               <l>Goods we inherit dayly, and Poſſeſſion,</l>
               <l>O that in goodnes were the ſame ſucceſſion.</l>
               <l>For then before his ſoule to Heauen he breathed,</l>
               <l>He had to each of vs a part bequeathed</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18353:26"/>
               <l>Of his true wealth: and cloſing thus his eyes,</l>
               <l>Would haue inrich'd his Sex with legacies.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sebaſtian Smith, Alumnus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>ANd is he dead? Immortall creature! thou</l>
               <l>Whom the proud heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſport to immantle now!</l>
               <l>Was Death ambitious? muſt he ſeaze on thee</l>
               <l>In th' Alphabet of thy mortality?</l>
               <l>Did hee o'retake thy life? and waſt thou got</l>
               <l>In ripeneſſe to be man, when thou waſt not?</l>
               <l>A ſtedfaſt conſcience well might ſhake to ſee</l>
               <l>Vertue at ſuch a pitch, as'twas in thee,</l>
               <l>Vntimely cropt. Thy predeceſſors lie</l>
               <l>In marble, not to teach thee Heraldry:</l>
               <l>Vertue gaue thee thy name, and made thee bee</l>
               <l>Vnto thine owne ſelfe, thine owne pedegree.</l>
               <l>When thou didſt liue, thou well didſt purify</l>
               <l>The droſſe of ſinne with pious Alchymy;</l>
               <l>And in thy time, no Latiniſt was hee,</l>
               <l>That declin'd Vertue by the name of Shee.</l>
               <l>Sorrow and teares now fit a blubberd eie,</l>
               <l>'Twas griefe, to thinke that thou ſhould'ſt euer die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eclipſe thy ſelfe, O thou Diaphanous Light,</l>
               <l>Let ſable darkneſſe canopied in Night,</l>
               <l>Baptize thee throughly: drawe and ſuck vp heere</l>
               <l>Such Sublunarie moiſture to thy Sphere,</l>
               <l>That, with a pious prodigie, thy beames</l>
               <l>May tranſubſtantiate themſelues to ſtreames,</l>
               <l>And beare a part in Sorrow: ſhould'ſt thou ſhine,</l>
               <l>Wee ſhould haue an Eclipſe, although not thine:</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18353:26"/>
               <l>Vntill his Conſtellation appeares,</l>
               <l>And dries the fertill moiſture of our teares:</l>
               <l>'Tis this we thirſt for: thirſt ſtill rauiſh vs,</l>
               <l>Wee will not grieue to be Hydropique thus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vitam relinquis, frueris antequam plenâ:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An ideò tantum veneras, vt exires?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Browne, Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>HVnc quòd ſurripuit mortis lex ſaeua, Deoſne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Creditis iratos? fuit hoc ſapientia, amor<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Numen tam ſacrum ſuperi inuidere nefandis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tantus ineſt animis coeleſtibus ardor amoris.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vt te mors perdat (numen mortale) rogauit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Matris opem, tantum haud potuit deuincere ſola:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>En ipſam mortem inualidam, vireſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> petentem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alterius, mortis non ſufficit vna poteſtas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed victus tandem es, dudùm ſtatione peractâ,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Excepit gaudente polo te regia coelì.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Viue illic igitur, ſubiecta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſydera calca,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dulce onus Atlanti, tam grato pondere preſſo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inuidiſſe iuuat, luctus haec vna voluptas.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non ſatìs in paruas tibi mors ſaeuire tabernas?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nobilium turres ambitioſa petis?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Improba, coniunctoſne iuuat ſèiungere fratres,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quos ſolùm poſſis corpore, mente nequis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Te nimìs anguſtam noſtrae ſenſere querelae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tu ſola in noſtram non ſatis inuidiam.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18353:27"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heu quid iam ſupereſt? fatis nolentibus ipſis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nitemur nomen deripuiſſe rogis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In chartis ipſis accreſcet gloria, quod<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dij nollent, ipſi carmina noſtra dabunt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nil opus eſt tumulo, hunc erexit propria virtus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illi cuiuſuis pectus erit tumulus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Eduardus Cluues, Commenſalis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>OVtinàm poſſent imitari carmina luctus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fraternos, feretro vt ſint ea digna tuo:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non illo meliùs quiſquam lugere, tuòue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quis poterat fato nobiliore frui.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inuidioſa alijs haec gloria mortis, erit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Talis abhinc luctûs ambitioſus honor.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Euan. Seys, Commenſalis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>Is't the reward of vertue to become,</l>
               <l>The ſubiect of vntimely Martyrdome?</l>
               <l>No ſooner can wee put on honeſty,</l>
               <l>But grimme death darts at our mortality.</l>
               <l>Did not death lately act this tragicke part,</l>
               <l>In butchering the innocenteſt heart,</l>
               <l>That hee ere hit? who beeing truly good,</l>
               <l>Thought vertue made him nobler then his bloud.</l>
               <l>T' was but the wit of death to kill him now</l>
               <l>In's infancy, when like a tender bough,</l>
               <l>Hee might him this or that way bend at pleaſure;</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:18353:27"/>
               <l>Had hee prorogu'd his end, and lent him leaſure,</l>
               <l>To nurſe his free-borne vertues, ſturdy death</l>
               <l>Had not with eaſe ſuckt out his vitall breath.</l>
               <l>Though young in yeeres hee was, yet old in good,</l>
               <l>To ſhew, that goodnes not in old age ſtood:</l>
               <l>His age and body told vs hee was yong,</l>
               <l>His courage, prou'd him old, and witty tongue.</l>
               <l>T' was not one combat with our enemy,</l>
               <l>(Which like graſſe mowes downe our mortality)</l>
               <l>That could ſubdue his courage, hee had two,</l>
               <l>To ſhew, that more then mortalls hee could doe.</l>
               <l>When t'was ſuppos'd from vs hee was departed,</l>
               <l>Hee ſtreight reuiu'd (and ſo ſeem'd double hearted)</l>
               <l>And ſtrongly ſet on death: but after ſent</l>
               <l>His forward ſoule to th' heau'nly regiment.</l>
               <l>Yet his Ghoſt walkes, his heyre of what was good,</l>
               <l>His liuing Sepulcher, by whoſe hot blood</l>
               <l>Our teares dry vp: in this reioyce wee may,</l>
               <l>That partiall death tooke not them both away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et moritur virtus? hoc viuida Muſa negauit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hìc iacet ille ſuis qui vidit ſaecula cunis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grandeuus<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> puer: quem ſat vixiſſe Sorores</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Senſerunt, cum vix tentaſſet uiuere; tantis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Noſter abundauit virtutibus alter Apollo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sacratos cuius cineres licet haec breuis vrna</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Contineat, vix terra animam, caeliue tenerent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non rabidae mortis tormentum hebetaret amorem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui caſtam effundens animam, ſic voce locutus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Viue tuo, frater, noſtro quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tempore viue.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Paſtilew, Alumnus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18353:28"/>
            <head>Vpon the Meaſels.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHy did our Anceſtors in former time,</l>
               <l>Account it for a grand detected crime,</l>
               <l>To feed on Swines-fleſh? What great worke might be</l>
               <l>The cauſe of that ſo ſtrange Antipathie?</l>
               <l>Could that commanding Miracle you knowe</l>
               <l>Amongſt the <hi>Gadarens,</hi> amaze them ſo?</l>
               <l>Would that ſame ſtiffe-neck'd race, for ſuch a ſight,</l>
               <l>Torture their ſtomake and their Appetite?</l>
               <l>'Twas not the Beaſt they loath'd, her durty haire</l>
               <l>Could not pollute her fleſh, nor did they care</l>
               <l>Where ſhe did wallow laſt, but ſurely theſe</l>
               <l>Abhorr'd them firſt for that corrupt diſeaſe</l>
               <l>They ſtill inherit; and this cauſe alone,</l>
               <l>May well excuſe their ſuperſtition.</l>
               <l>Sure, were thy ſickneſſe and diſeaſe but knowne,</l>
               <l>And how thou diedſt of their infection,</l>
               <l>They would be curſt euen now, and wiſht the fate</l>
               <l>That thoſe two thouſand had; nay men would hate</l>
               <l>Their very name; And this vnhappy newes</l>
               <l>It were enough to make vs all turne Iewes.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>IOHN STANHOPE <hi>Anagrama.</hi> NO HOPE IN HAST.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Haſte ſpoileth hope whilſt after hope he flies,</l>
               <l>Haſte giues the fall, and here on ground he lyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Will. Kitchen, Commen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:18353:28"/>
            <head>De tempore Comitiorum OXONIENSIVM in quibus mortuus eſt.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>FAllax vita hominis, nimis<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fallax;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quidni fabula? quae breuis, minuta eſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae toto tenet, occupat<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> curſu</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Actus quinque ſed OPTIMIS negatos.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quaenam iſtud noua crimen execrandum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Parcis addita Parca perpetrauit?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aut quo? quo properas Amor Parentum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebo pulchrior &amp; ſorore Phoebi?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eheu! fabula, quae breuis, minuta,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Feſtinata tibi eſt: tibi merenti</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cornìcis vetulae quater ſenectam;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Interrupta tibi eſt; &amp; in * ſecundo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Actu (non rediturus) exijstì.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Elſynge, Armig. Fil. natu max. Commenſalis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:18353:29"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>STanopum primâ rapuit mors atra iuventâ,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Delicias veſtri (turba novena) chorj.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si quem fortè mori vetuerunt carmina Muſae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nùnc venam &amp; vires Caſtalis vnda probet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui deſunt vitae numerentur laudibus anni</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic fiet manes, &amp; ſine morte cimis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dic quibus in terris coelum capit vrna? Stanopi</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hac quâ parte iacet merſa fauilla. ſapis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quid parios lapides &amp; marmora ſacra paratis?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quem nemo deflet, Pyramis iſta decet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stillant Heliades, ſtillant Electra Camaenae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vt tegat exanimem ſuccina gemma cutem.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic decuit clarum tumnlo lucere Stanopum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui vixit nostrae Sydus honoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> togae.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Io. Wall, Sa. The. Dr. ex Aed. Ch.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18353:29"/>
            <head>Of the tranſportation of his Corps from <hi>Oxford</hi> to <hi>Shelford</hi> in a Coach.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HEre <hi>Charon</hi> Coach-man, gently waft fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Thames</l>
               <l>To Trent, this Body: iog him not; he dreames</l>
               <l>Now of <hi>Eliah's</hi> Charriot, and a Paire</l>
               <l>Of Angels drawing him along the Aire,</l>
               <l>In ſtead of Horſe. Innocence may not feele</l>
               <l>The Iuſtice of a Purgatorie wheele.</l>
               <l>I prethee vſe him gently: I reſigne</l>
               <l>Into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy hands a thing, that whilſt 'twas mine,</l>
               <l>Deſeru'd the curt'ſie, if th'adſt pau'd the way</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> boughes or ruſhes; as the Iewes, the day</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he Paſſion, did entertaine</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eruſalem,</hi> for him home againe.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>n, goe before, let vs diuide</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> rankes, and I will ride</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>rd; now or ne're we goe</l>
               <l>Vnto ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>grimage of woe:</l>
               <l>For we do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> all: He that ſhall aske</l>
               <l>Me who is dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h put me to a Taske</l>
               <l>I cannot anſwere well; yet, if we know</l>
               <l>Effect by Cauſe, and demonſtration ſhew</l>
               <l>A neceſſary Conſequence; I gueſſe,</l>
               <l>The King, not's Father, had the loſſe, no leſſe,</l>
               <l>(If the Natiuitie be caſt of's breeding)</l>
               <l>Honour can follow ſo direct Proceeding.</l>
               <l>Were I not tongue-tide, or ſome reference</l>
               <l>Muzled my Pen from telling of the ſence</l>
               <l>Of this young Myſtery, I could read who</l>
               <l>Remembred God in's youth, and neuer knew</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18353:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:18353:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18353:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:18353:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18353:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:18353:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:18353:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18353:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18353:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18353:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18353:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:18353:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18353:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:18353:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:18353:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18353:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:18353:38"/>
               <l>How to run out in <hi>Oxford,</hi> nor th' expence</l>
               <l>Of Sinne or Money, 'les 'twere to diſpence</l>
               <l>Vnto the Poore. You that diſpute the Caſe</l>
               <l>Of Mans Saluation, thinking it a grace</l>
               <l>To vſe a neat diſtinction, learne to doe</l>
               <l>Of him, that learn'd the <hi>Theorie</hi> of you.</l>
               <l>Harke, the Bels ring, away, peace dolefull ſound,</l>
               <l>Let vs enioy our woes, doe not confound</l>
               <l>Still Paſſions with loud Muſicke: yet ring on,</l>
               <l>Helpe to make vp ſolemne Proceſſion,</l>
               <l>Now is Rogation weeke. Here <hi>Oxford</hi> ends:</l>
               <l>And here <hi>Northampton</hi>-ſhire: <hi>Leſter</hi> extends</l>
               <l>It ſelfe vnto this Bridge, and then we be</l>
               <l>Riding along in <hi>Notingham:</hi> A Tree,</l>
               <l>Though young, yet wither'd, did diſtinguiſh one;</l>
               <l>Another was diſtinguiſh't by a Stone,</l>
               <l>Fit for an Epitaph. Here I ſow'd a Teare,</l>
               <l>Which I will reape againe when I come there.</l>
               <l>Thus euery thing's an Enblem that we ſee,</l>
               <l>To repreſent to vs our miſery.</l>
               <l>The poore o'th Pariſhes accompany</l>
               <l>Vs in our Progreſſe, and as lowd doe cry</l>
               <l>Vnto, as for the dead: and ſome in loue</l>
               <l>Drowne their Religion, calling God aboue,</l>
               <l>(As if the dead their Prayers did auaile)</l>
               <l>To bleſſe the Burden that we goe withall.</l>
               <l>Thus we found pittie, though we found no eaſe;</l>
               <l>And Trauelling will ſeldome bring releaſe.</l>
               <l>For Care will be a Horſe-man. Now I'ue grieu'd</l>
               <l>Threeſcore and ten, to <hi>Shelford,</hi> and haue liu'd</l>
               <l>The date of Man in Miles; the ſurpluſage,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Dauids,</hi> is a trouble, not an Age.</l>
            </lg>
            <signed>I. Hodſdon.</signed>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18353:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
